A Guide to the Janet L. Cameron Collection, 1931-2001
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Janet L. Cameron Collection, 1931-2001
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-021
0.4 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection includes biographical information about the life and career of Janet L. Cameron, a food and nutrition specialist with the Virginia Cooperative Extension from 1931-1964. Most of the collection consists of publications written by Cameron and others.
Cameron, Janet L., 1904-1986
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Janet L. Cameron Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2000.
Alternate Form Available
Many of the photocopied photographs in this collection are available online through Virginia Tech's Imagebase at: http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/browse.php?folio_ID=/culinary/camer.
Biographical Note
Janet L. Cameron was born in Atlanta, Georgia, in 1904. She began her college education at Georgia State College for Women, but later transferred to Columbia University. She worked as a home demonstration agent in New York, beginning in 1924. She graduated from Columbia in 1926. Following the completion of her Master's in Human Nutrition from Columbia University in 1931, she worked as a Foods and Nutrition Specialist with the Virginia Cooperative Extension until 1964. She died in 1986 in Florida.
Mary L. Thompson completed a Bachelor's degree from Harrisonburg State College in 1924. She later completed a Master's of Science at Columbia University. From 1924 to 1940, she served as a home demonstration agent in four different Virginia counties. In 1942, Thompson began work as a Food Specialist for the Virginia Cooperative Extension Service. She continued with the Extension Service until her retirement in 1963.
Additional biographical information on both Cameron and Thompson is available as part of the collection.
Scope and Content
The collection includes biographical information about the life and career of Janet L. Cameron, a food and nutrition specialist with the Virginia Cooperative Extension from 1931-1964. Most of the collection consists of publications written by Cameron and others. There is also a folder of materials relating to Mary L. Thompson, a frequent co-author of Cameron's and the Virginia Home Economics Association.
A scopecontent of the publications is listed at the folder-level in the " Contents List" below. Please note: The collection does NOT contain all the publications on the list in Box 1-Folder 3.
Arrangement
Please note: Materials in this collection were donated in a single binder. Although materials were removed from the binder for processing and long-term storage, the content was split into two series. Series I: Janet L. Cameron Materials remains in its original order. Series II: Publications, are in chronological order within each subseries.
Series I: Janet L. Cameron Materials includes a personal and professional biography written in 2001, photocopies of photographs of Cameron, and some of Cameron's publications from her tenure with the Virginia Cooperative Extension. It also contains copies of Cameron's obituary, memoirs by friends, and copies of poems written by Cameron for the retirements of colleagues, as well as Virginia Home Economics Association agendas and pamphlets.
Materials in this series are in their original order.
Series II: Publications consists of three subseries. Subseries I: Janet L. Cameron Publications includes a collection of pamphlets and publications written by Cameron between 1935 and 1962. Subseries II: Janet L. Cameron and Mary L. Thompson includes publications written by both women. Subseries III: Mary L. Thompson Publications contains several publications by Cameron's frequent co-author. Topics of publications in all three subseries include, but are not limited to, home demonstration, nutrition/food groups/diet, food economy (especially during World War II), holiday desserts, and entertaining. Most items in this series are Virginia Cooperative Extension bulletins, circulars, and pamphlets.
Publications are arranged in chronological order within each subseries.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Ms2001-004, Ann A. Hertzler Collection. A finding aid for this collection is available online: http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/vt/viblbv00716.xml.frame
RG 26/2, Agricultural Extension Service (now Virginia Cooperative Extension Service) Records. A brief description of the materials in this University Archives record group is available online: http://spec.lib.vt.edu/archives/guide/rg26.htm.
Index Terms
Persons:
Thompson, Mary L., (Mary Lippard); Cameron, Janet L., 1904-1986
Subjects:
Virginia Cooperative Extension; History of Food and Drink; Faculty
Contents List
- Series I: Janet L. Cameron Materials, 1931-2001.
  - Biographical Information. (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Supplementary Information. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Mary L. Thompson Biographical Information. (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Virginia Home Economics Association Materials. (Box-folder 1-15)
- Series II: Publications, 1935-1974.
  - Janet L. Cameron Publications.
    - Publications List. (Box-folder 1-3)
    - 1930-1939 (Box-folder 1-4)
      Bibliography
      Cameron, Janet L. Recipes for 4-H Club Members in Food and Nutrition Work, Circular E-320, March 1935.
      ---. Recipes for Home Demonstration Club Members in Food and Nutrition Work, Circular E-319, March 1935.
      ---. Community Meal Planning, Circular E-338, February 1937.
      ---. Christmas Delights, [1930s].
      ---. Six-Way Cookie Mix, [1930s].
    - 1941 (Box-folder 1-5)
      Cameron, Janet L. Yeast Breads, 1940.
      ---. Nutrition News--Food for Defense Issue, Number 25, 303, 1941.
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson II: Our Vegetable Needs and How to Get Them, Number 25,147, July 1941.
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson IV: Fruits Add Pep and Variety as well as Food Value, Number 25, 147, July 1941. (2 copies)
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson VI: Milk and Dairy Products, Number 25, 147, July 1941.
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson VII: The Staff of Life, How Bread and Cereals Can Enrich the Diet, Number 25, 147, July 1941.
      ---. Nutrition News--A Definite Yardstick for Good Nutrition, Number 25, 137, July 1941.
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson IX: When Eggs 'N Cheese Get Together, Number 25, 147, July 1941.
      ---. Nutrition for National Defense--Virginia Refresher Course, Lesson X: General Summary of Nutrition Refreshers Discussions, Number 25, 147, July 1941.
      ---. How Do Your Meals Stack Up?, Number 22, 404, 1941.
      ---. Virginia Apples in Any Meal, Number 19, 844, [1941?].
    - 1942-1949 (Box-folder 1-6)
      Cameron, Janet L. Saving Fruits and Vegetables by Drying, Brining, Sulphuring, Circular E-360, April 1942.
      ---. Carry a Victory Lunch for Work or School, Number 22, 225, September 1942.
      ---. Holiday Food Suggestions, Number 25, 748, 1943.
      ---. Holiday Sugar Savers, MF-7, [1943?].
      ---. Making Bread at Home, Circular 383, June 1944.
      ---. Holiday Sugar Savers 1945, MF-62, August 1945.
      ---. Planning the Family Food Supply, Circular 400, May 1946.
      ---. Magic Meals from Prepared Frozen Foods, MF-165, April 1948.
      ---. Better Pies and Pastry, Number 19, 799, [1940s?].
      ---. Make Your Daily Bread and Cereal Whole Grain or Enriched, Number 25, 503, [1940s?].
      ---. When You Take the Cake!, Number 19, 847, [1940s?].
    - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 1-7)
      Cameron, Janet L. Home Made Mixes Save You Time and Money, Bulletin 184, September 1950.
      ---. One Mix for 16 Different Pies, MF-249, July 1951.
      ---. Making Bread at Home, Circular 383, Revised, November 1952.
      ---. Homemade Mixes: They Save You Time and Money, Bulletin 184, Reprinted, January 1952.
      Todd, Mabel, and Janet L. Cameron. Food is Tops! Take Off the Pounds Safel y, Bulletin 219, August 1954.
      Cameron, Janet L. The Best Planned Meals, MF-298, January 1956.
      ---. Essentials of Adequate Diet, MF-351, Revised, October 1956.
      Todd, Mabel, and Janet L. Cameron. Keen Teens Eat Well!, Circular 702, October 1956.
      Cameron, Janet L. Food Sense and Nonsense, MF-364, September 1957.
      ---. The Cookie Jar, MF-192, December 1959.
    - 1960-1964 (Box-folder 1-8)
      Cameron, Janet L. Congealed and Frozen Desserts, MF-378, Re-Run August 1960.
      ---. Weight Control: How to Get and Hold Your Desirable Weight, Leaflet 131, November 1961.
      ---. Around the World Foods, Circular 789, January 1963.
      ---. Suggestions to Home Demonstration Agents for Organizing Weight Control Groups, MF-306, January 1964.
    - 1974, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
      Cameron, Janet L. Freezing Fruits, MF-130, May 1974.
      ---. Eat More Sweet Potatoes, Number 25, 746
  - Janet L. Cameron and Mary L. Thompson Publications.
    - 1944, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 1-10)
      Cameron, Janet L., and Mary L. Thompson. Canning for the Home, Bulletin No. 128, Revised, June 1944.
      ---. Outdoor Meals! 4-H Project for Senior Boys and Girls, Bulletin 225, May 1955.
      ---. Apples Around the Clock, Bulletin 231, September 1955.
      ---. Merry Christmas from Our Kitchen to Yours, MF-352, October 1956.
      ---. Recipes for Cottage Cheese Dishes, Bulletin 249, June 1957.
      ---. Low Calorie Desserts, MF-297, March 1957.
    - 1958-1959, 1962 (Box-folder 1-11)
      Cameron, Janet L., and Mary L. Thompson. Making Bread at Home, Circular 383, Revised, July 1958.
      ---. Buffet Meals for Special Occasions, MF-315, September 1958.
      ---. Ways to Get More Milk in the Diet, MF-389, June 1959.
      ---. Snacks and Simple Refreshments II, MF-260, May 1959.
      ---. Quick and Easy Desserts, Circular 911, July 1962.
      ---. Apples Around the Clock, Bulletin 231, Revised, March 1962.
  - Mary L. Thompson Publications.
    - 1950-1952 (Box-folder 1-13)
      Thompson, Mary L. Cakes and Decorative Icing, MF-230, September 1950.
      ---. Pies and Meringue--Light and Fluffy as a Cloud, MF-232, October 1950.
      ---. Christmas Suggestions, Circular 518, November 1950.
      ---. Homemade Desserts, Bulletin 197, January 1952.
      ---. Beverages and Simple Refreshments, MF-260, January 1952.
      ---. Christmas is What You Make It, MF-275, October 1952.
    - 1953-1962 (Box-folder 1-14)
      Thompson, Mary L. Relish the Basic Seven, MF-288, August 1953.
      ---. Easy Nutritious Desserts, MF-247, Revised, February 1955.
      ---. Buying Food Is Big Business-Your Business, MF-380, August 1958.
      ---. Oven Meals, MF-138, November 1962.